A machine can now not only beat you at chess but also outperform you in debate.
如今，机器不仅能在国际象棋上打败你，还能在辩论中胜过你。
Last week, in a public debate in San Francisco, a software program called Project Debater beat its human opponents, including Noa Ovadia, Israel’s former national debating champion.
上周，在旧金山举行的一场公开辩论中，一个名为 Project Debater 的软件程序击败了人类对手，其中包括以色列前全国辩论冠军诺阿·奥瓦迪亚。
Brilliant though it is, Project Debater has some weaknesses.
Project Debater 虽然很出色，却也有一些弱点。
It takes sentences from its library of documents and prebuilt arguments and strings them together.
它的资料库里存有文档和预先构建好的论点，它从中提取句子，再把这些句子串在一起。
This can lead to the kinds of errors no human would make.
这可能导致一些人类绝不会犯的错误。
Such wrinkles will no doubt be ironed out, yet they also point to a fundamental problem.
这类小毛病无疑会被消除，但它们也暴露出一个根本性的问题。
As Kristian Hammond, professor of electrical engineering and computer science at Northwestern University, put it: “There’s never a stage at which the system knows what it’s talking about.”
正如美国西北大学电气工程与计算机科学教授克里斯蒂安·哈蒙德所说：“这个系统在任何阶段都不知道自己在说什么。”
What Hammond is referring to is the question of meaning, and meaning is central to what distinguishes the least intelligent of humans from the most intelligent of machines.
哈蒙德所说的是意义问题，而意义正是区分最不聪明的人与最聪明的机器的核心所在。
A computer works with symbols.
计算机处理的是符号。
Its program specifies a set of rules to transform one string of symbols into another.
它的程序规定了一套规则，把一串符号转换成另一串符号。
But it does not specify what those symbols mean.
但程序并不规定这些符号是什么意思。
Indeed, to a computer, meaning is irrelevant.
事实上，对计算机来说，意义无关紧要。
Humans, in thinking, talking, reading and writing, also work with symbols.
人类在思考、谈话、阅读和写作时，也要处理符号。
But for humans, meaning is everything.
但对人类来说，意义就是一切。
When we communicate, we communicate meaning.
我们交流时，交流的是意义。
What matters is not just the outside of a string of symbols, but the inside too, not just how they are arranged but what they mean.
重要的不只是一串符号的外表，还有其内里；不只是符号如何排列，还有它们是什么意思。
Meaning emerges through a process of social interaction, not of computation, interaction that shapes the content of the symbols in our heads.
意义产生于社会互动的过程，而非计算的过程，正是这种互动塑造了我们头脑中符号的内容。
The rules that assign meaning lie not just inside our heads, but also outside, in society, in social memory, social conventions and social relations.
赋予意义的规则不仅存在于我们的头脑之中，也存在于头脑之外，存在于社会之中，存在于社会记忆、社会习俗和社会关系之中。
It is this that distinguishes humans from machines.
正是这一点把人类与机器区分开来。
And that’s why, however astonishing Project Debater may seem, the tradition that began with Socrates and Confucius will not end with artificial intelligence.
正因如此，无论 Project Debater 看起来多么惊人，始于苏格拉底和孔子的传统都不会终结于人工智能。